Finding Aid for Ward Family Papers 1860-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ward Family Papers 1860-1964 1900-1940
Ward family.
31.2 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
8 oversize folders
Orchard Lake, Michigan, family, with various business interests, including lumbering and land transactions (in Michigan, California, West Virginia, and British Columbia), and also active in the development of the Orchard Lake area, especially from the 1920s to the 1940s; Correspondence files of individual family members, subject files detailing family interests and activities, business and legal records, maps, blueprints, and photographs.
87212 Aa 2 AC
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Elizabeth Devine, Dolly Golding, and Ann Spaeth, daughters of Harold Ward (donor no. 7249 ) in 1985. Additional materials were donated by Suzanne Devine (donor no. 11259 ), daughter of Elizabeth Devine, in 2015.
The collection is open for research.
David Ward, one of Michigan's noted lumber barons, was born in Keene, New York, in 1822. He and his parents and nine brothers and sisters moved to Newport, Michigan, in 1836. Nathan Ward, David's father, was a farmer and surveyor, who taught David the art of surveying and surviving in the woods of Michigan. David's frequent trips with his father into the woods, however, caused him to suffer from bronchitis and while recuperating from a bout in 1840 he began to study medicine. Over the next ten years he taught school and took a variety of surveying jobs, and when financially able, studied medicine at Cleveland Medical College (1847-1848) and the University of Michigan (1850-1851). He received his Doctor of Medicine degree from the University in the Spring of 1851.
David Ward had two goals in life: to be a full-fledged medical doctor and a wealthy man. Once he had achieved his first goal, he set out to acquire wealth and he did so by putting his surveying talents to work. He surveyed the vast tracts of pine land in northern Michigan for large operators and charged as his fee, one-fourth of the lands he surveyed. Over the years, through surveying and purchasing, he acquired 800 million feet of pine in Michigan. In addition, he acquired extensive holdings of redwood lands in California, coal lands in West Virginia, and pine lands in Vancouver. By the time he died in 1900, at the age of seventy-eight, he had achieved his second goal. Newspapers estimated his estate to be worth $15 million.
David and his wife, Elizabeth Perkins Ward, raised their three sons and one daughter on a two-hundred acre farm on Orchard Lake, which he purchased in 1862. They moved to Detroit in 1881 because of Mrs. Ward's rheumatism, but spent summers at the farm, and in 1893, Ward built a $30,000 house on the lake. In his later years, his son Willis, grandson Franklin B., and son-in-law George Root helped him run his business concerns. They were named executors of the David Ward Estate.
Willis continued his involvement in Ward businesses after his father's death, and was particularly concerned with the sale and/or development of Ward properties. In addition, he devoted a good deal of time to the development of the Orchard Lake area. He contributed the land which facilitated the organization of the Orchard Lake Country Club, purchased Apple Island on Orchard Lake for conservation purposes, and was active in the good roads movement. He was an author, who wrote extensively on the history of Orchard Lake, an inventor, and was interested in poultry, cattle, and fruit farming. He and his wife Mabel had two children: Marjorie, who married Frederick S. Strong, Jr., a career Army officer and an early founder of the city of Orchard Lake; and Harold, who married Virginia Palmer of Detroit.
Harold carried on his father's business concerns after Willis died in 1944. He also served on the board of directors of Kingswood School Cranbrook in Bloomfield Hills, and like his father, was actively involved in the Orchard Lake Country Club and in the development of Orchard Lake. Harold died in 1983.
The majority of the Ward Family collection is comprised of materials generated by Willis Ward and his son, Harold, and thus reflect the life of the family in the twentieth century. The strengths of the collection rest on materials which document upper-class family life in the first three decades of this century; the development of the Orchard Lake area in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s; the extensive Michigan land holdings of the Ward family; and the history of the lumber town of Deward, Michigan. The researcher should be aware that there are only limited materials in the collection which document either David Ward's business pursuits in Michigan or his personal life. The researcher should supplement those materials with use of Ward's published autobiography.
There are six series which comprise the Ward collection: Personal; Correspondence; Land Holdings; Photographs; Architectural Drawings; and Maps. Whenever possible the original order of materials in the first three series has been maintained.
Subjects:
British Columbia.; California.; Deward (Mich.); City planning--Michigan--Orchard Lake.; Land use--United States.; Land use--Michigan.; Logging--United States.; Lumbering--United States.; Orchard Lake (Mich.); Orchard Lake Country Club.; Suburbs--Michigan.; Vancouver Island (B.C.); West Bloomfield (Mich.: Township); West Virginia.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Boats.; California.; Deward (Mich.); Lumber industry.; Orchard Lake Country Club.; Orchard Lake (Mich.); Richmond (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Roads--Michigan--Oakland County.; Williams College.; Winter.; Winter sports.; Yale University.; Ward family.
Subjects - Maps
Antrim County (Mich.)--Maps.; California--Maps.; Charlevoix County (Mich.)--Maps.; Cheboygan County (Mich.)--Maps.; Crawford County (Mich.)--Maps.; Emmet County (Mich.)--Maps.; Kalkaska County (Mich.)--Maps.; Kanawha River Valley (W. Va.)--Maps.; Logging--United States--Maps.; Manistee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Orchard Lake (Mich.)--Maps.; Otsego County (Mich.)--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Maps.; Vancouver Island (B.C.)--Maps.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series (5.2 linear feet) is divided into two subseries: Family and Individuals.
  - Family
    The Family subseries primarily contains materials which pertain to the interests and concerns of several generations of the Ward Family. Of greatest importance are those files of materials on the Orchard Lake Country Club, which can be very useful in documenting the early history of the club. They should be supplemented by the use of Harold Ward's files on the country club in the Correspondence series.
    - Birth Dates (incomplete) (Box 1)
    - Historical (Box 1)
      (mostly on Orchard Lake area)
      (see also genealogy in blueprints folder)
    - Obituaries (David, Elizabeth, Harold) (Box 29)
    - Orchard Lake
      - Boat Club (Constitution, Articles of Association, By-laws, Minutes) 1872-1873 (Box 1)
      - Country Club
        - General, 3 folders (Box 1)
        - Annual Statements (Box 1)
        - Golf Course (mostly re: construction) (Box 1)
        - Long Term Planning Committee minutes 1952 (Box 1)
        - Membership (Lists, correspondence with prospective members) 1926-1927 (Box 1)
        - Newsletter 1928-1964 (Box 1)
      - Schools brochure undated (Box 1)
      - Water Levels (Box 1)
    - Taxes, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Writings on Lumber Industry (no author) undated (Box 1)
    - Obituaries, 1834-1944 (Box 31)
  - Individuals
    The Individuals subseries is arranged by family members. The folders contain material which will help the researcher better understand the personalities of Ward family members, particularly David, his sons, Charley and Willis, and his grandson, Harold. It is also the portion of the collection which best documents David Ward's estate. There are two linear feet of legal documents, maps, and bound and unbound correspondence pertaining to the execution of the estate. The bound volumes of correspondence, which are in very fragile condition, are comprised of the letters of the family law firm involved in work with the estate.
    By studying the estate files, the researcher will learn of the extent of Ward property holdings at the time of David's death. (David Ward materials were received in two accessions. The second group of estate files more thoroughly documents land holdings in West Virginia.) In addition, along with the use of Willis Ward's business correspondence, insight can be gained into the establishment and running of the town of Deward. Deward was located just north of Grayling and was built as part of David Ward's estate to cut the pine on 70,000 acres of timber in Crawford, Kalkaska, and Otsego Counties. Per instructions from Ward in his will, the logging was completed in 1912, after which Deward became a ghost town. The insight gained from these files primarily concerns the business affairs connected with the Deward logging operations.
    - Ward, David
      - Library, Index to (Box 1)
      - Medical School, Class Notebook (Cleveland College) (Box 1)
      - Newspaper articles 1886 (Box 29)
      - Writings (autobiographical) (Box 1)
      - Estate
        - General, 14 folders (Box 2)
        - Correspondence (volumes)
          - July 19, 1900-February 18, 1902 (Box 2)
          - February 20, 1902-January 26, 1903 (Box 3)
          - January 26, 1903-December 15, 1903 (Box 3)
          - December 16, 1903-July 25, 1904 (Box 3)
          - July 25, 1904-June 8, 1905 (Box 3)
          - June 8, 1905-April 18, 1906 (Box 3)
          - April 18, 1906-March 30, 1907 (Box 3)
          - April 1, 1907-March 28, 1908 (Box 3)
          - March 30, 1908-January 5, 1909 (Box 3)
        - General Correspondence (foldered)
          - Correspondence 1913-1914 (Box 3)
          - Correspondence and miscellaneous 1914-1917 (Box 3)
        - Journal of the estate of David Ward 1900-1903 (Volume 1)
        - West Virginia
          - General
            - 1902 (Box 3)
            - 1903 (Box 3)
            - 1903 1908 (Box 3)
            - 1904 (Box 3)
            - 1905-1907 (Box 3)
              (includes Henry Christy, Advance Lumber Co., Cleveland, OH)
          - Correspondence 1881-1899 (Box 30)
          - Correspondence and miscellaneous matters 1900-1901 (Box 30)
          - Correspondence 1915
            - Brown, James F. (Box 30)
            - Flournoy, P.W. (Box 30)
            - Hartman, Joseph (Box 30)
            - Patterson, John H. (Box 30)
            - Pratt, F.S. (Box 30)
            - Pribble, J.D. (Box 30)
            - Romine & Snyder (Box 30)
            - Staunton, F.M. (Box 30)
          - Data 1901-1903 (Box 30)
          - Land
            - Coal leases 1898-1903 (Box 30)
            - Papers in connection with making coal leases 1901 (Box 30)
            - Lease of coal lands 1903 (Box 30)
              (includes proposed Hanna lease)
            - Coal lease matters 1902-1903 (Box 30)
              (includes Hanna option)
            - Approval of modification of coal lease 1915 (Box 30)
              (2 copies)
            - Coal land sale correspondence 1918 (Box 30)
            - Summary of Annual Output of Coal Mined 1904-1912 (Box 30)
              (Kellys Creek & Hughs Creek Coal Companies)
            - Conveyances to David Ward in Kanawha County undated (Box 30)
            - Permission for right of way down Hughes Creek 1904 (Box 30)
            - Venable's report on estate coal lands on Kanawha River in connection with outcrop survey of no. 5 seam undated (Box 30)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 30)
      - Receipts 1860s-1910s, 4 folders (Box 30)
      - Student Notebook (Box 31)
        (University of Michigan Medical School)
      - Correspondence 1885-1896, 15 folders (Box 31)
    - Ward, Elizabeth (estate materials) (Box 4)
    - Ward, Henry (estate materials) (Box 4)
    - Ward, Charles (Box 4)
    - Ward, Willis
      - Biographical (Box 4)
      - Inventions, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Stock purchases and sales (Volume 2)
      - Letters to Editors (re: taxes and tax legislation) (Box 4)
      - Valentines (Box 4)
      - Writings (Box 4)
    - Ward, Harold
      - Biographical (Box 4)
      - Aviation (Box 4)
      - Financial (Box 4)
      - Kingswood School, Cranbrook, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (fifteen linear feet) is also arranged by family members. The original order in which the correspondence was kept has been maintained. There are, therefore, files arranged chronologically and files arranged by correspondent. Under Willis Ward, for example, the researcher will find incoming correspondence arranged by family member, including parents, wife, and children, that is of a distinctly personal nature. There are also extensive correspondence files arranged chronologically, which relate to his business concerns. This dual arrangement also holds true for Harold Ward. Contents list entries describe, for each family member, how his or her correspondence is arranged.
  The Correspondence series is the most informative series on Ward Family life. There are letters from Charles Ward, the somewhat wayward son of David, to his parents throughout the 1890s. They describe his life in New York State as a florist and detail his attempts to return to his parents' good graces. When studied in conjunction with the David Ward estate files, the researcher will better understand the animosity between Charles and the other Ward heirs. The largest portion of this series is comprised of Willis and Harold Ward's correspondence. The letters to and from family members are interesting because they document, in some detail, the everyday life of a wealthy, close-knit family. Children describe their school life, summers on the lake, travels to Europe, and interactions with friends and other family members. Parents give advice to their children and frequently comment to one another on their children's activities. They describe their own travels, both in the United States and abroad, and discuss national and world events. The business correspondence of Willis, which is quite extensive, and Harold, primarily concerns family land holdings.
  - Ward, Charles (mostly outgoing to Mother and Father)
    - 1881 1886 (Box 5)
    - 1893 (Box 5)
    - 1894, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1895 (Box 5)
    - 1896 (Box 5)
    - 1897 (Box 5)
    - 1898 (Box 5)
    - 1899-1903 (Box 5)
      contains interesting letters re: David Ward estate
  - Ward, Willis
    - Family Members (incoming from)
      - Ward, David (father) 1899-1900 (Box 6)
      - Ward, Elizabeth (mother) 1893, 1899-1900 (Box 6)
      - Ward, Mabel (wife) 1902-1915, undated (Box 6)
      - Ward, Marjorie (daughter) 1899-1927, undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Ward, Harold (son) 1900-1935, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Friends (incoming from)
      - Lane, James 1899-1900 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Chronological (primarily business related)
      - 1895, 1900-1902 (Box 6)
      - 1902-1903 (Box 6)
      - April 1903-December 1, 1904 (Box 7)
      - December 1, 1904, October 11, 1905 (Box 7)
      - October 11, 1905, June 1, 1906 (Box 7)
      - June 1, 1906-December 31, 1906 (Box 7)
      - January 1, 1907-October 15, 1907 (Box 7)
      - October 15, 1907-February 1, 1908 (Box 8)
      - February 1, 1908-August 1, 1908 (Box 8)
      - August 1, 1908-December 1, 1908 (Box 8)
      - December 1, 1908-May 1, 1909 (Box 8)
      - May 1, 1909-November 1, 1909 (Box 9)
      - November 1, 1909-May 24, 1910 (Box 9)
      - May 24, 1910-December 1, 1910 (Box 9)
      - December 1, 1910-May 1, 1911 (Box 9)
      - May 1, 1911-September 1, 1911 (Box 10)
      - September 1, 1911-November 20, 1911 (Box 10)
      - November 20, 1911-February 3, 1912 (Box 10)
      - February 3, 1912-June 17, 1912 (Box 10)
      - June 18, 1912-September 6, 1912 (Box 11)
      - September 7, 1912-November 11, 1912 (Box 11)
      - November 12, 1912-March 5, 1913 (Box 11)
      - March 5, 1913-June 15, 1913 (Box 11)
      - June 15, 1913-October 6, 1913 (Box 12)
      - October 6, 1913-December 17, 1913 (Box 12)
      - December 17, 1913-May 30, 1914 (Box 12)
      - June 1, 1914-August 18, 1914 (Box 12)
      - August 18, 1914-October 24, 1914 (Box 13)
      - October 27, 1914-February 13, 1915 (Box 13)
      - February 13, 1915-June 3, 1915 (Box 13)
      - June 3, 1915-July 31, 1915 (Box 13)
      - August 1, 1915-October 10, 1915 (Box 14)
      - October 10, 1915-January 1, 1916 (Box 14)
      - January 1, 1916-June 1, 1916 (Box 14)
      - June 1, 1916-September 1, 1916 (Box 14)
      - September 1, 1916-February 1, 1917 (Box 15)
      - February 1, 1917-June 15, 1917 (Box 15)
      - June 15, 1917-December 20, 1917 (Box 15)
      - December 8, 1917-November 9, 1918 (Box 15)
      - November 1918-August 20, 1919 (Box 16)
      - August 20, 1919-May 1920 (Box 16)
      - May 1920-November 28, 1920 (Box 16)
      - 1921 (Box 16)
        (folders 1-2 of 4)
      - 1921 (Box 17)
        (folders 3-4 of 4)
      - 1922 (Box 17)
      - March 1, 1921-August 1, 1922. (Box 17)
      - August 1, 1922-January 1, 1924 (Box 17)
      - January 1, 1924-December 31, 1924 (Box 17)
      - 1925 (Box 18)
      - January 1, 1926-December 31, 1927 (Box 18)
      - January 1, 1928-1929 (Box 18)
      - 1930, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - 1931-1937, 0.5 linear feet (Box 19)
      - Incoming correspondence, 1889 (Box 31)
  - Ward, Mabel
    - Family Members (incoming from)
      - Ward, Willis undated, 1900-1912 (Box 19)
      - Ward, Harold 1910-1915 (Box 19)
    - Other (one letter from "Hattie") (Box 19)
  - Ward, Harold
    - Family Members (incoming from)
      - Ward, Willis (father)
        - 1899-1911 undated (Box 19)
        - 1912-1919 (Box 19)
        - 1926, 1927, 1933, 1940 (Box 19)
      - Ward, Mabel (mother) 1910-1915, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Ward, Marjorie (sister) 1908-1916 (Box 19)
    - Leisure, George 1931-1943 (Box 20)
    - Orchard Lake Country Club
      - 1926, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - 1932-1959 (Box 20)
    - Chronological (primarily business related)
      - 1923-1925, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 20)
        (folders 1-4 of 7)
      - 1927-1928 (Box 21)
        (folders 5-7 of 7)
      - 1928-1930 (Box 21)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 21)
  - Other family
    - Ward, Marjorie (Box 21)
    - Strong, Frederick (husband of Marjorie) 1925 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
- Land Holdings
  Land Holdings (six linear feet), the third series in the collection, is comprised of correspondence and legal documents which pertain to Ward property in California, Michigan, West Virginia, and Vancouver (Alice Lake). The series is arranged into five subseries: a general subseries, and one for each geographical location. The researcher is advised to examine the general subseries prior to studying materials which relate to a particular location. It is comprised of documents, primarily correspondence of Willis and Harold, that were kept together and concern one or more of the major land holdings of the family.
  In the California, West Virginia, and Vancouver subseries, there are files which provide background and summary-type information on Ward holdings. For California, there are additional files of materials from companies set up by the family to sell its redwood holdings. The Michigan subseries is further divided into three sections: Northern Michigan, Orchard Lake, and West Bloomfield. The Northern Michigan files can be used to trace the disposition of Ward land holdings in the 1920s. The Orchard Lake and West Bloomfield sections are interesting for the researcher studying the land development of these two areas in the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s. The materials from companies set up by the Wards to oversee the sale of their properties, in addition to the business correspondence of Willis and Harold (see Correspondence series) are particularly helpful in this regard.
  - General (mostly correspondence)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 21)
    - 1920s (Box 21)
    - 1930s (Box 21)
      (folders 1-3 of 4)
    - 1930s (Box 22)
      (folder 4 of 4)
    - 1930s-1940s (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - California
    - General (Box 22)
      (folders 1-8 of 18)
    - General (Box 23)
      (folders 9-18 of 18)
    - Blue Creek Company
      - Financial statements 1937-1951 and depositions from lawsuit, 1954, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Ward Redwood Company
      - General (Box 23)
        (folders 1-3 of 11)
      - General (Box 24)
        (folders 4-11 of 11)
      - Annual Meetings
        - 1938-1940, 1947-1950 (Box 24)
        - 1951-1955 (Box 24)
        - 1956-1959 (Box 24)
  - Michigan
    - Northern Michigan
      - General (mostly correspondence) 1920s, 6 folders (Box 25)
      - Chamberlain, Robert: Opinions re: Ward Land Holdings (Box 25)
      - Harvey, Sandy (correspondence with Willis Ward), 1919 (Box 25)
    - Orchard Lake
      - General (Box 26)
      - Land Use Restrictions (Box 26)
      - Orchard Land Company (mostly correspondence) (Box 26)
      - General (Box 26)
      - 1926-1933, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - 1927-1929 (Box 26)
    - West Bloomfield
      - General, 5 folders (Box 26)
      - Property Prices 1920s, 1930s (Box 26)
      - Residential Suit (Box 26)
      - Road Matters (Box 26)
      - Sale of lands (correspondence) (Box 26)
      - West Bloomfield Company 1930s, 1940s (Box 26)
  - Vancouver
    - General (mostly correspondence) 1920s-1940s, 5 folders (Box 27)
    - Tax Problems (Box 27)
  - West Virginia
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
    - Kanawa and Elk River Railroad, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - Coit, 7 folders (Box 31)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (two linear feet) is alphabetically arranged by topic. There are very good positive images of Ward family members and of logging operations in California and Michigan.
  - Family
    - Ward Family Members, 5 folders (Box 27)
      (includes glass negatives, see also oversize box 29)
    - Homes and Surrounding Grounds (Box 28)
      (see also oversize box 29 for additional photographs and for blueprints of home)
    - Ward, Harold, Photograph Album 1907-1910 (Box 28)
      (includes pictures of Europe)
    - Chamberlain Family (Box 28)
    - Fay Family (Box 28)
    - Lee Family (Box 28)
    - Other, includes glass negatives (Box 28)
  - Foreign countries
    - Egypt (trip down the Nile) 1911 (Box 28)
    - Puerto Rico (Office of Chief Commissary, U.S. Army) undated (Box 28)
      in Box 29
    - Russia (Vladivostok harbor) 1920s, 4 negatives (Box 28)
  - Fletcher, Ed (Box 28)
  - Land holdings and logging
    - General unidentified undated (Box 28)
    - California
      - Undated, 4 folders (Box 28)
        (see also Box 29)
      - 1950s (Box 28)
    - Michigan
      - Undated (Box 28)
      - 1871-1872 (Box 28)
      - 1880s (Box 28)
      - Deward, Michigan 1911, undated (Box 28)
    - Vancouver Island, Alice Lake undated (Box 28)
  - Michigan lakes properties undated (Box 28)
  - Michigan roads 1916, 1916 undated (Box 28)
    (includes negatives)
  - Orchard Lake Country Club undated (Box 28)
  - Sailing (unidentified) undated (Box 28)
  - Winter sports scenes undated (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - Oversize photographs (Box 29)
- Architectural drawings
  - Reference copies (Box 29)
  - Architectural drawings (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
    [Staff use only: use reference copies in Box 29]
  - Engineering and architectural drawings (Map-case 1, Folder 2)
    (include blueprints of cottage, log lighter, and highway smoothing plane)
- Maps